Finding Aid for John Warner Fitzgerald papers, 1952-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Warner Fitzgerald papers 1952-1982
Fitzgerald, John Warner, 1924-
851273 Aa 2
Attorney, Michigan State Senator, and Judge; correspondence and other papers primarily from the period when he served in the Michigan State Senate, 1959-1964.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
12 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Judge and Mrs. John W. Fitzgerald (donor no. 4510 ) and came to the library in 1969 and 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
John W. Fitzgerald was born in Grand Ledge, Michigan on November 14, 1924. He graduated from Michigan State University (1947) and the University of Michigan Law School (1954). He was elected to the Michigan State Senate in 1958, 1960, and 1962. In 1964, he was elected judge in the 3rd District of the Court of Appeals. He later served two terms on the Michigan Supreme Court, 1974-1983.
The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Michigan State Senate, 1959-1964; University of Michigan Law School; Photographs; Campaign Materials; Michigan Supreme Court; and Press files.
Subjects:
Apportionment (Election law)--Michigan.; Eaton County (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1964.; Fitzgerald, John W. (John Warner), 1924-2006; Grand Ledge (Mich.); Judges--Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Republican Party (Mich.); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Scranton, William Warren, 1917-2013; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Law School.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fitzgerald, John W. (John Warner), 1924-2006
Contributors:
Adams, Paul L. (Paul Lincoln), 1908-; Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Chamberlain, Charles E. (Charles Ernest), 1917-2002; Hannah, John A., 1902-1991; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Harvey, James, 1922-; Johansen, August E. (August Edgar), 1905-1995; Joiner, Charles Wycliffe, 1916-; Kelley, Frank J. (Frank Joseph), 1924-; Leskinski, T. John, 1925-; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; Peterson, Elly Maude, 1914-2008; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Ryan, Harold Martin, 1911-; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1958-February 1963, 27 folders (Box 1)
  - March 1963-March 1964, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - April 1964-1965, 7 folders (Box 3)
- Michigan State Senate 1959-1964
  - Newspaper clippings 1959-1964 (Box 3)
  - State legislators and legislative committee assignments 1959 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Crime and Delinquency Council undated (Box 3)
  - Schools and school aid 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Republican state convention 1963 (Box 3)
  - Copies of bills before the State Legislature 1960-1964 (Box 3)
  - Engineering report for freeway, I-496 (Lansing area) 1964 (Box 3)
  - Constitutional Convention, the new state constitution, and its proposed implementation 1960-1964 (Box 3)
  - Apportionment
    - Testimony of August Scholle on the matter of apportionment 1961 (Box 4)
    - General information on apportionment 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, publicity, etc. on the question of apportionment 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Hearings of the state judiciary committee on the problem of apportionment 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Legal briefs and petitions brought before the State Supreme Court in the "apportionment case" 1963-1964 (Box 4)
    - Legal briefs and petitions brought before the U.S. District Court in the "apportionment case" 1963-1964 (Box 4)
    - Legal briefs and petitions brought before the U.S. Supreme Court in the "apportionment case" 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    - Study by Charles W Shull, entitled Legislative Apportionment in Michigan, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Printed material concerning plans for legislative apportionment (Box 4)
  - Taxes and tax reform 1963 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Employment Security Appeal Board 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Presidential campaign of Nelson Rockefeller and William Scranton 1964 (Box 4)
  - Book by Charles Press and Oliver Williams, entitled State Manuals, Blue Books and Election Results, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
- University of Michigan Law School
  - Course notes 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Course notes 1953-1954 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Portrait of John W. Fitzgerald (Box 6)
  - Portraits, JWF as part of groups, miscellaneous (Box 7)
- Campaign Materials
  - Michigan State Senate 1959-1964, 2 folders (Box 7)
    (include some legislative miscellanea)
  - Michigan Court of Appeals (Box 7)
  - Michigan Supreme Court (Box 7)
- Michigan Supreme Court 1977-1981
  - Topical file
    - Abeyance cases (Box 7)
    - Board of Law Examiners 1980 (Box 7)
    - Chief Justice (Box 7)
    - Class Action Rule (Box 7)
    - Conferences, minutes 1981 (Box 7)
    - Cooley Law Review (Box 7)
    - Cooley Law School 1978-1981, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Court Administration (Box 7)
    - Court Administrator (Box 7)
    - Deferred Grand Summaries 1981 (Box 7)
    - Disqualification of Convicted Felons from Jury Service (Box 7)
    - Felony murder (Box 7)
    - Fitzgerald, Judge John W.
      - Memos 1981 (Box 7)
      - Personal 1977-1982, 6 folders (Box 7)
      - Annual financial reports (required by Canon 6C) (Box 7)
    - Friend of the Court (Box 8)
    - Insurance -- professional liabilities for judges (Box 8)
    - Invitations 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Judges Liaison Committee 1981 (Box 8)
    - Judicial Coordinating Committee (Box 8)
    - Judicial Tenure Commission 1981 (Box 8)
    - J.U.R.I.S. program (Box 8)
    - Jury Plans (proposed analysis and evaluation) (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous 1981 (Box 8)
    - State Appellate Defender (Box 8)
    - State Court Administrative Office (Box 8)
    - Status reports 1981 (Box 8)
    - Wayne County Court reorganization 1981 (Box 8)
  - Legislative Apportionment 1982
    - Reports, legislative plans, memoranda, court briefs and other documents (Box 8)
    - Reports, legislative plans, memoranda, court briefs and other documents (Box 9)
    - Reports, legislative plans, memoranda, court briefs and other documents (Box 10)
      (continued)
  - Chronological file
    (copies of outgoing correspondence)
    - 1955 1977-1981, 6 folders (Box 11)
- Press file (largely State Supreme Court)
  - 1977, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 1978-1981, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Re Judge Thomas Kavanagh (Box 12)
  - Re Judge John B. Swainson (Box 12)
  - Earlier clippings (State Senate career) (Box 12)
    (unprocessed)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Adams, Paul L. (Paul Lincoln), 1908-
Mar. 24, 1960, Mar. 24, 1961, Apr. 24, 1961
Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969
Mar. 24, 1960
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
Oct. 7, 1963
Chamberlain, Charles Ernest, 1917-
Oct. 7, 1963, Feb. 20, 1964
Hannah, John A., 1902-
Jan. 8, 1963
Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.
Mar. 13, 1961
Harvey, James, 1922-
Jan. 18, 1962, Sept. 6, 1962, Mar. 4, 1963
Johansen, August Edgar, 1905-
Apr. 22, 1963
Joiner, Charles Wycliffe, 1916-
Jan. 29, 1965
Kelley, Frank J. (Frank Joseph), 1924-
Apr. 9, 1963, Nov. 13, 1963, Jan. 22, 1964, Feb. 20, 1964
Leskinski, T. John, 1925-
Mar. 12, 1963, Apr. 5, 1963
McKay, Frank D., 1883-1965.
Nov. 18, 1963
Peterson, Elly, 1914-
Sept. 23, 1963, Oct. 18, 1963, Oct. 22, 1963, Oct. 23, 1963, Oct. 30, 1963
Romney, George W., 1907-
Apr. 3, 1963, May 14, 1963, May 21, 1963
Ryan, Harold Martin, 1911-
Jan. 9, 1963, Apr. 25, 1963
Swainson, John Burley, 1925-
Mar. 16, 1961, Nov. 20, 1963